Joseph Manuel

Full Stack Software Developer & Experienced Data Analytics/Visualisation

Professional

Dunfermline, Edinburgh, Scotland UK

🕠 mickeyjoe75 🛚 in mjmconsultinc 📓 9473322 💆 @MjMSquawk

Joe is a highly driven Full Stack Software Developer and globally experienced Management Consultant with extensive multi site, multi system/platform, off-shoring & outsourcing experience. Joe has a proven track record in implementing and driving best in class Workforce planning applications, Telephony systems & Business Intelligence applications for blue-chip companies across Europe & Asia over a career spanning 19 years.

SKILLS

Data Analysis

Master

tableau | t-sql | python | r | verint wfm |

avaya | powerbi

Back End Development

Intermediate

java | ruby | go

TDD

Intermediate

minitest | junit | mocha | chrome dev tools

Front End Development

Intermediate

javascript | html | css | bootstrap | dom |

iquery | sass

Databases

Master

postgresql | ms sql server | mongodb

Mobile Development

Intermediate

android | kotlin | flutter | xamarin

Frameworks

Intermediate

react and react native | redux | express |

sinatra | django | flask

WORK EXPERIENCE

Trainee Full Stack Software Developer at CodeClan March 2018- June 2018

https://codeclan.com/

A 16 week Full Stack Software Development Bootcamp with a curriculum that is project-based and includes: • Version control via Git and GitHub • Object Oriented Programming (Ruby, Java, Javascript) • TDD in Ruby with MiniTest, in Java using JUnit and Mockito, and in JavaScript using Mocha • Web app development with Sinatra, Express and React • HTML and CSS • Database design with PostgreSQL and MongoDB • Use of Ajax and Document Object Model manipulation • A teaching environment comprised of agile methodologies in 3-week learning blocks, 1-week project sprints and daily morning scrums. The CodeClan four-month intensive course is SQA approved and awards a PDA in Software Development

(SCQF level 8).

- A web application "ProActiveWFM" using Ruby on Rails and CRUD and RESTful methods
- A vanilla JavaScript Full Stack Web app group project "Education App" with no frameworks and utilising NPM packages, Webpack, NodeJs, MongoDB & Express
- An Android todo list app "proActiveScheduler"

Senior Consultant - Operations Planning and Analytics at IP Integration Ltd October 2015- March 2018 https://www.ipintegration.com/

Managed Analytics for clients using Tableau platform, well versed with Tableau Desktop, Tableau server and Tableau online. Performed extensive GAP analysis in the project as there were numerous 'As-Is' and 'To-Be' conditions. Building, publishing customized interactive reports and dashboards, report scheduling using Tableau server. Created action filters, parameters and calculated sets for preparing dashboards and worksheets in Tableau.Intraday Task Management: Interaction Analytics:-Speech, text and social media analytics can connect the customer journey and provide actionable insight. Voice Self Service/Biometrics:-Automated customer service can reduce the cost to serve and improve overall customer experience. Technology Roadmaps:-Ensure alignment of your technology strategy towards the achievement of targeted business outcomes. Discovery Programmes:-From assessing candidate functions for automation to business process analysis and re-engineering. Programme Management:-Full cycle programme management from feasibility and definition through to operationalisation.

Founder & Managing Director at Numero Uno Apps Development Ltd. & SMJ Business Services Ltd. July 2014- Current

http://numerounoapps.com/

Strategic Consulting in Business Intelligence (Tableau,SQL)& MIS |Website Hosting&Development| Mobile Apps Development||Bid/Price Modelling for BPO/Outsourcing Contracts|| Resource/Capacity Planning||Advanced Excel Modelling|| WFM Optimisation(Verint)|| Shift/Staffing Reviews/Optimisation||Dialler/Data Strategy|| Project Management.

Interim BI & WFM Consultant at Portsmouth Health Limited July 2015- October 2015 http://www.phlgroup.co.uk/

Set up MI and Planning department for an NHS contractor providing Out of Hours GP cover service.

Interim BI & WFM Consultant at benenden group August 2014- February 2015 https://www.benenden.co.uk/

WFM tools and practices optimisation: * Building a Capacity and Resource plan for the Benenden Healthcare Member services through Advanced Excel templates and optimizing the use of Verint Impact 360 Ver.11 system and Speech Analytics and Avaya AACC platform. *Training and developing the onsite resources and build a business case for WFM department.

Senior Manager - BI, WFM & Special Projects at Thames Water October 2012- July 2014 https://www.thameswater.co.uk/

Heading the Business Intelligence, Reporting, WFM and Real Time Command Center for Thames Water Customer Services, business lead role in CS Change and Transformation projects, leading a multi site, multi discipline team for the Thames Water utilities RP & BI function covering all planning and MI disciplines for a multi-site operations through Capacity & Resource Planning, Forecasting, Scheduling, Intra-day & MI for Customer Services organisation

- Opex savings of £2M in Contact Centre budget in the current FY through optimised resource plans and improved forecast process for Billing and Operations Contact Centres
- Introduction and set up of a Business Intelligence team for Customer Services by migration of MS ACCESS and VBA based reporting into an SQL reporting Server.

Management Consultant (Freelance) at Ember Services October 2011 - October 2012 http://www.embergroup.co.uk/

Business Intelligence and Analytics •SQL query, SAP Business Objects and Excel VBA expertise •Automation and design of Reports / Dashboards and KPI definition for major blue-chip UK companies •Setting up and off-shoring of MI function •Managing and optimizing support areas such as WFM, Dialler and MI teams across UK and India •Forecasting& Planning for Inbound / Outbound / Back office / Mail Room workloads •Call flow analysis, call driver / root-cause analysis, campaign, agent performance analysis •Data modelling, data mining, data warehousing techniques •Project Management of transition and transformation programmes / projects •Predictive Dialler / data optimisation and analysis and expertise on high impact dialling/campaign set up strategies and Ofcom compliance

Head of Operational Support at HCL Technologies November 2006- October 2011 https://www.hcltech.com/

Member of the Senior Mgmt team and Business Steering Group, Directly responsible and heading the Strategic Capacity Planning,Resource Planning,Dialler Management and Reporting and Management Information functions for HCL Northern Ireland across both sites in Belfast and Armagh with 2000+ employees Expertise on Business Analytics and Six Sigma methodology

Finance, Sales & Customer Service Roles at Various Roles February 1998- November 2006 https://www.ibm.com, http://www.vertexgroupindia.com, http://www.fulfordindia.com/

Various roles in Finance, Marketing, Sales and Customer Service in India spanning over 8 years, included transitioning business process from US for Sprint PCS Customer Services

EDUCATION

Software Bootcamp Information Technology at CodeClan

2018 - 2018

Major courses: object oriented programming (ruby, java, javascript)

tdd in ruby with minitest, in java using junit and mockito, and in javascript using mocha

web app development with sinatra, express and react | database design with postgresql and mongodb |

use of ajax and document object model manipulation | html and css

Grade: SCQF level 8

Business Administration & Management at University of Ulster 2010 - 2011

Major courses: advanced diploma in management practice | one week induction in the boston business school, ma

Grade: Advanced Diploma in Management Practice

Bachelor of Science(Hons) at Mahatma Gandhi University

1995 - 1998

Major courses: maths | chemistry | physics | english

Grade: BSc(Hons)

LANGUAGES

English

Native speaker

Hindi

Native speaker

Urdu

intermediate

Malayalam

Native speaker

Tamil

intermediate

Punjabi

intermediate

INTERESTS

Swimming

Marathoner

Badminton

Skills acquired:

belfast marathon 2011, time(5hrs)

Stock Market

Skills acquired: crytpo | blockchain | forex